export const SOCIALSTUDIESA2003 = [

{
id: "question1",
question: "1. Sharing of kola nuts in Islamic marriage rites signifies",
A: "Stability of the marriage",
B: "Love of the marriage",
C: "Payment of bride wealth to the bride’s family",
D: "Payment of compensation to the bride’s family",
answer: "C. payment of bride wealth to the bride's family",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question2",
question: "2. Child delinquency is mainly caused by",
A: "Broken homes",
B: "Peer influence",
C: "Corporal punishment",
D: "Teenage pregnancy",
answer: "A. broken homes",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question3",
question: "3. Duolocal marriage is common among the",
A: "Akan",
B: "Ga",
C: "Ewe",
D: "Gonja",
answer: "B. Ga",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question4",
question: "4. For a marriage to be stable the couple needs to be",
A: "Religious",
B: "Innovative",
C: "Accommodating",
D: "Wealthy",
answer: "C. Accommodating",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question5",
question: "5. A burning sensation in the male genital organ and the discharge of yellowish threads of pus are symptoms of",
A: "Syphilis",
B: "Gonorrhea",
C: "Candidiasis",
D: "Bilharzia",
answer: "B. Gonorrhoea",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question6",
question: "6. One of the arguments against the use of condoms is that",
A: "They are very expensive",
B: "They are not easily available",
C: "Couples feel shy to use them.",
D: "They can interfere with sexual pleasure",
answer: "D. they can interfere with sexual pleasure",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question7",
question: "7. Parents could effectively handle the problems of their adolescent children through",
A: "Providing their needs at all times",
B: "Submitting to their desires",
C: "Making rigid rules at home",
D: "Counselling and tolerance",
answer: "D. counselling and tolerance",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question8",
question: "8. Population census in Ghana is conducted under the auspices of the",
A: "Ministry of Economic Planning",
B: "Ministry of information",
C: "Statistical Service",
D: "Electoral Commission",
answer: "A. Ministry of Economic Planning",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question9",
question: "9. Mortality rate in Ghana has declined mainly because of",
A: "Road safety campaigns",
B: "The absence of ethnic conflicts",
C: "Easy access to balance diet",
D: "Improved medical facilities",
answer: "D. improved medical facilities",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question10",
question: "10. One disadvantage of polygamy is that",
A: "It is limited only to illiterates",
B: "It violates the rights of women",
C: "It is financially costly",
D: "The women re not involved in family decision",
answer: "C. it is financially costly",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question11",
question: "11. A self actualising person is associated with",
A: "High determination",
B: "Abundant wealth",
C: "Good health",
D: "Higher education",
answer: "A. high determination",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question12",
question: "12. The two major factors that affect an individuals personality are",
A: "Age and experience",
B: "Heredity and environment",
C: "Religion and wealth",
D: "Education and health",
answer: "B. heredity and environment",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question13",
question: "13. “What a man must be he must be”, according to Abraham Maslow’s hierarchy of needs, this is attained at the level of",
A: "Self-actualization needs",
B: "Physiological needs",
C: "Safety and security needs",
D: "Status needs",
answer: "A. self actualisation needs",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question14",
question: "14. Individuals can develop their capabilities through  \nI.	good medical care  \nII.	encouragement from parents  \nIII.	self determination  \nIV.	assistance from peers",
A: "I and II only",
B: "III and IV only",
C: "I, II and III only",
D: "II, III and IV only",
answer: "D. II, III and IV only",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question15",
question: "15. A negative effect of the application of modern machines in production is",
A: "Low production",
B: "High cost of living",
C: "Displacement of labour",
D: "Mismanagement of resources",
answer: "C. displacement of labour",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question16",
question: "16. The scientific principles underlying the invention of the aeroplane are  \nI. law of flotation  \nII.	Principles of air-lift  \nIII.	Aerodynamics  \nIV.	Hydrolysis",
A: "I and II only",
B: "II and III only",
C: "I, II bind IV only",
D: "II, III and IV only",
answer: "B. II and III only",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question17",
question: "17. The introduction of mathematics and-science programmes on radio and television is aimed at",
A: "Creating job opportunities for science teachers",
B: "Promoting science education",
C: "Generating revenue for scientific research",
D: "Fostering cooperation between science teachers",
answer: "B. promoting science education",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question18",
question: "18. The establishment of technical and vocational institutions in Ghana is aimed at producing manpower to",
A: "Enhance the exploitation of resources",
B: "Develop the agricultural sector of the economy.",
C: "Exploit and utilize the natural resources of the country",
D: "Develop the scientific knowledge in schools",
answer: "C. exploit and utilize the natural resources of the country",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question19",
question: "19. Scientific and technological knowledge is acquired to solve human problems through",
A: "Ingenuity and creativity",
B: "Capital accumulation",
C: "The establishment of grammar schools",
D: "The availability of natural resources",
answer: "A. ingenuity and creativity",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question20",
question: "20. Increased productivity results in",
A: "Drastic decrease in taxes",
B: "The retrenchment of workers",
C: "The folding-up of business organizations",
D: "Higher wages for workers",
answer: "D. higher wages for workers",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question21",
question: "21. One of the most effective ways of ensuring national integration is to",
A: "Adopt common cultural practices",
B: "Adopt one national language",
C: "Promote inter-ethnic marriages",
D: "Promote the teaching of ethics in schools",
answer: "C. promote inter-ethnic marriages",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question22",
question: "22. The primary unit for the socialization of the child is the",
A: "Family",
B: "Church",
C: "Community",
D: "Peer group",
answer: "A. family",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question23",
question: "23. Girl-child education is necessary because it enhances",
A: "The maintenance of peace",
B: "Effective parenting",
C: "Honest leadership",
D: "The training of teachers",
answer: "B. effective parenting",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question24",
question: "24. The value of education is measured by",
A: "Excellent academic performance",
B: "One’s ability to earn a living",
C: "One’s contribution towards societal development",
D: "How intelligent a person can be",
answer: "C. one's contribution towards societal development",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question25",
question: "25. Ethnocentrism undermines",
A: "Economic independence",
B: "Social stability",
C: "Religious freedom",
D: "Educational reforms",
answer: "B. social stability",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question26",
question: "26. The belief that the ancestors need peace before the celebration of an annual festival leads to",
A: "An imposition of curfew",
B: "The offering of sacrifices",
C: "The cleansing of ancestral stools",
D: "A ban on noise making",
answer: "D. a ban on noise making",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question27",
question: "27. Shaving of the hair and sleeping with a corpse are associated with",
A: "Purification rites",
B: "Widowhood rites",
C: "Puberty rites",
D: "Initiation rites",
answer: "B. widowhood rites",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question28",
question: "28. It is necessary to preserve our cultural heritage because it will",
A: "Ensure continuity of society",
B: "Make our culture unique",
C: "Create more employment",
D: "Promote national reconciliation",
answer: "A. ensure continuity of society",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question29",
question: "29. If a journalist is arrested by the police and detained for more than seventy-two hours, which fundamental human-right has been infringed upon?",
A: "Right to freedom of speech and expression",
B: "Right to live",
C: "Right to freedom of association",
D: "Right to personal liberty",
answer: "D. Right to personal liberty",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question30",
question: "30. Which of the following is the most important shared value needed in a heterogeneous society?",
A: "Loyalty",
B: "Hospitality",
C: "Humility",
D: "Tolerance",
answer: "D. Tolerance",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question31",
question: "31. The Coat of Arms of Ghana signifies",
A: "Prosperity and development",
B: "Growth and stability",
C: "Power and authority",
D: "Freedom and justice",
answer: "D. freedom and justice",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question32",
question: "32. The rich Ghanaian cultural heritage is practically demonstrated during",
A: "Religious functions",
B: "Traditional festivals",
C: "National sports festivals",
D: "National dance competitions",
answer: "B. traditional festivals",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question33",
question: "33. Which of the following is classified as a material culture?",
A: "Dance",
B: "Music",
C: "Pottery",
D: "Folklore",
answer: "C. Pottery",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question34",
question: "34. A democrat is fair and firm while an autocrat is",
A: "Oppressive",
B: "Benevolent",
C: "Progressive",
D: "Co-operative",
answer: "A. oppressive",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question35",
question: "35. Paternal leadership is based on",
A: "Hereditary influence",
B: "Patrilineal inheritance",
C: "Family relation",
D: "Age and experience",
answer: "B. patrilineal inheritance",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question36",
question: "36. One disadvantage of a democratic system of government is that",
A: "In times of crises, decision making is delayed",
B: "Certain powerful persons easily dominate the political scene",
C: "The goals of the government are not achieved",
D: "Initiative and participation are discouraged",
answer: "A. in times of crises, decision making is delayed",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question37",
question: "37. Decentralization in public administration promotes",
A: "Corruption at the local level",
B: "Participatory democracy",
C: "Dictatorship in administration",
D: "Ineffective central government",
answer: "B. participatory democracy",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question38",
question: "38. Which of the following is a sub-regional international organization",
A: "The United Nations Organization (U.N.O)",
B: "The Non-Aligned Movement (N.A.M)",
C: "The Commonwealth",
D: "The Economic Community of West African States (ECOWAS)",
answer: "D. The Economic Community of West African States (ECOWAS)",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question39",
question: "39. Under the 1992 Constitution of Ghana, the main function of the Council of State is to",
A: "Appoint members of the Executive",
B: "Approve laws made by Parliament",
C: "Act as an advisory body to the government",
D: "Declare a state of emergency in times of crises",
answer: "C. act as an advisory body to the government",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question40",
question: "40. Which of the following political institutions arc wrongly paired in terms of their functions?  \nI.	Executive administration of Justice  \nII.	Judiciary policy implementation  \nIII.	Legislature law making  \nIV.	Electoral Commission conduct of elections",
A: "I and II only",
B: "I and III only",
C: "III and IV only",
D: "I, II and IV only",
answer: "A. I and II only",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question41",
question: "41. International co-operation is based on the principles of",
A: "Self-reliance",
B: "Inter-dependence",
C: "Neutrality",
D: "Self-sufficiency",
answer: "B. inter-dependence",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question42",
question: "42. A negative impact of Ghana’s economic co-operation with the developed world is that",
A: "Standard of living falls",
B: "Political instability is promoted",
C: "Political sovereignty is lost",
D: "Local initiative is destroyed",
answer: "D. local initiative is destroyed",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question43",
question: "43. Wildlife reserves are habitats for",
A: "Protected flora",
B: "Dangerous mammals",
C: "Endangered animals",
D: "Tamed animals",
answer: "C. endangered animals",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question44",
question: "44. A progressive community is the one which",
A: "Willingly undertakes community development projects",
B: "Is content with existing projects",
C: "Relies on government grants for its development",
D: "Depends only grants from non-government organizations",
answer: "A. willingly undertakes community development projects",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question45",
question: "45. The Keta sea defence project in Ghana is an example of",
A: "Land fragmentation",
B: "Land redistribution",
C: "Land reclamation",
D: "Land demarcation",
answer: "C. land reclamation",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question46",
question: "46. At the national level self-reliance for economic growth calls for development of",
A: "Import trade",
B: "A human resource",
C: "Religious belief",
D: "Mullti-party politics",
answer: "B. human resource",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question47",
question: "47. Positive change in attitudes and values help to",
A: "Improve living standards",
B: "Promote local initiative",
C: "Improve moral standards",
D: "Promote peaceful co-existence",
answer: "D. promote peaceful co-existence",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question48",
question: "48. A country’s per capita income can be changed if",
A: "The economy grows faster than the-population",
B: "The population grows faster than the economy",
C: "The population and the economy grow at the same rate",
D: "Rural-urban migration is controlled",
answer: "A. the economy grows faster than the population",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question49",
question: "49. Poor attitudes towards work can be changed through",
A: "Labour sanctions",
B: "Re-orientation programmes",
C: "Lucrative pension schemes",
D: "Tax exemptions",
answer: "B. re-orientation programmes",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question50",
question: "50. The main sources of finance available to a private entrepreneur are  \nI.	Personal savings  \nII.	Commercial bank loans  \nIII.	Government treasure bills  \nIV.	World Bank loans",
A: "I and IV only",
B: "II and III only",
C: "II, III and IV only",
D: "I, II and III only",
answer: "D. I, II and III",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},



]